Hello, and welcome to Lesson 16 of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
大家好 欢迎来到Wolfram U的微积分入门课程第16课
The topic for this lesson is maxima and minima.
本节课的主题是最大值和最小值
Let’s begin with a brief overview of the lesson. Many mathematical problems involve
首先 简单介绍一下本课的内容 很多数学问题都涉及到
getting the best solution for a task. In fact, people use mathematics when they really do want the best solution for a task.
求解任务的最佳解决方案 事实上 当真正需要求解任务的最佳解决方案时 人们往往会使用数学
There’s a word for best solution. It’s usually called optimal solution,
最佳解决方案通常被称为最优解
and the whole process of getting such a solution is called optimization.
而得到最优解的过程叫优化
Okay. As an example of optimization, let’s take this function f[x] and plot it.
举一个优化的例子 给定函数f[x] 并绘制其图像
The plot is a downward-opening parabola, and the highest value of this plot is clearly at (0, 3).
函数图像是向下开口的抛物线 显然 函数的最大值点为（0，3）
In this case, our notion of best or optimal is the highest value. Typically, one wants to talk about
在这个例子中 最佳或最优的定义就是最大值 通常情况下 人们
maxima and minima in various problems. The goal of this lesson is to develop a process
在各种问题中都会讨论最大值和最小值 本节课的目标 是确定一个流程
for finding maxima or minima for different problems using derivatives.
用来借助导数寻找不同问题的最大值或最小值
Various people use optimization in different ways. For example, if you run a business,
不同的人使用不同的方式进行优化 例如 假设你经营一家企业
then clearly what you want to do is to maximize your profit and minimize your cost.
显然 你想要的是利润最大化、成本最小化
Even a plant knows that it must grow in such a way that it obtains the maximum amount of sunlight.
即便是植物 它们也知道需要获得最多的阳光以生存
A GPS system is designed to get you to a destination in either the shortest amount of time or distance.
GPS系统被设计为 让你在最短的时间或距离内到达目的地
In general, you have optimization problems which involve either finding the maximum or the minimum.
一般来说 优化问题涉及到寻找最大值或最小值
Differential calculus is really an excellent tool for solving these optimization problems.
微分学是解决优化问题的绝佳工具
In fact, that’s how the subject arose in the works of Fermat and other mathematicians.
事实上 在费马和其他数学家的作品中 优化课题就是这样产生的
Let’s now go ahead and talk about the notion of an absolute maximum or minimum.
首先讨论最大值和最小值的概念
A value f[c] is an absolute maximum of a function if its value is greater than or equal to
f[c]为函数最大值的条件是 该函数值大于或等于
every other value for the values in a certain set D where D is called the domain.
函数在某个集合D中的任意其他值（除c以外） 其中D称为函数定义域
When I say maximum and I say absolute maximum, I mean the very greatest value of a function.
当提及最大或绝对最大时 指的就是函数的最大值
Similarly, if one says absolute minimum, you mean the least value of a function on a certain set D.
类似地 如果是绝对最小 指的是函数在某一集合D上的最小值
For example, if we take the sine function, clearly its maximum is over here at π/2
举例说明 正弦函数 显然 它的最大值在π/2处
where it’s got a value of 1, and its minimum is at 3π/2 where it’s got the value −1.
函数值为1 而最小值在3π/2处 函数值为-1
Another term used for absolute maximum and minimum is global maximum and minimum.
绝对最大值和最小值又称为全局最大值和最小值
When you say absolute, it means the same thing as global.
绝对与全局的意思一样
Okay. Together, these maxima and minima are sometimes called the extreme values of the function.
最大值和最小值 有时也被称为函数的极值
In this case, we’re lucky. We had an absolute maximum and an absolute minimum.
在这个例子中 很幸运 函数有一个绝对最大值和一个绝对最小值
But in general, the best that you can hope for are so-called local maxima and minima.
总体而言 局部最大值和最小值是你应该期望的
For example, here is a function, a cubic function, and you can see quite clearly that
例如 这是一个三次函数 明显可以看到
this graph has got local maxima and minima. That’s the local maximum over here,
函数有局部最大值和最小值 局部最大值在这里
and that’s the local minimum over there, but if you go far away enough, the values will
这里是局部最小值 如果移动足够远 函数值将
go up or go down dramatically. The idea of a local maximum is that you have a value f[c]
剧烈增加或下降 局部最大值的概念是 一个函数值f[c]
which is more than other values for x near c, and similarly for local minima.
对于c附近的x 都有f[c]大于f[x] 类似的可以得到局部最小值的定义
Near depends upon the function of course, but that’s a nice way about talking about maxima and minima—
定义中的附近取决于函数 但这是一种讨论最大值和最小值很好的方式
by using the local definition rather than the global definition. In the case over here,
即使用局部最值的定义而不是全局最值的定义 上述例子中
there is a local maximum at that point and a local minimum at that point.
这是一个局部最大值点 这是一个局部最小值点
We’ll see that quite shortly. Of course, if you have an absolute maximum,
我们很快就能得到这一点 当然 如果是一个绝对最大值
that’s clearly a local maximum, and if you have an absolute minimum, that’s clearly a local minimum.
那显然也是一个局部最大值 如果是一个绝对最小值 那显然也是一个局部最小值
The fact that you have absolute maxima and minima is very special knowledge—
事实上 有绝对最大值和最小值点意味着包含特别的性质
much better than having local maxima or minima.
相比于局部最大值或最小值而言
Okay. Things could go wrong or be different in some cases. For example, if you have
在某些情况下 情况可能不同甚至出错 例如
the constant function like over here, the constant function 5, then clearly every real number is
像这样的常数函数5 那么显然每个实数5都是
an absolute maximum and minimum. On the other hand, if you have the cubic function over here,
绝对最大值和最小值 另一个例子 这里的三次函数
then you have neither an absolute or local maximum or minimum everywhere.
在任何地方都没有绝对或局部最大最小值点
These are very special cases which are worth remembering as we talk about maxima and minima.
这些都是在讨论最大值和最小值时需要记住的特殊情况
Namely, you could have situations in which you have everything being optimal or nothing being optimal.
也就是说 可能会出现任意点都是最优解 或没有点是最优解
Okay. Now the question is how do we find these extreme values, but even if we’re talking about that,
那么 现在的问题是 如何才能找到这些极值 尽管我们已经正在讨论这个问题
we need to figure out some conditions under which one can guarantee that they’re extreme values.
我们仍然需要找出一些极值点的条件 在这些条件下 可以保证它们是极值
This is what’s called the extreme value theorem. What that does is it gives you conditions
这就是极值定理 其作用是 提供了判断
for when a function is guaranteed to have extreme values. It says that if you have a function
一个函数存在极值点的条件 极值定理如下 一个
on a closed interval and that function is continuous—so you have a continuous function
闭区间上的连续函数
on a closed interval [a, b]—then that function will attain an absolute maximum
该函数必然存在一个绝对最大值
and an absolute minimum at some numbers c and d on the interval. As long as you have
和绝对最小值 分别在区间上的c和d处取得 只要你有
a continuous function and a closed interval, you are fine. For example, I have these three plots over here,
一个连续函数和一个闭区间 条件就可以成立 举例 这里有三张图
and the black dots will indicate that that side of the interval is closed, and the white dots
黑色点代表区间的这一侧是封闭的 而白色点
or the blank dots will indicate that you have an interval side which is not closed.
或者空白点意味着区间这一侧不封闭
In the first example, you see you’ve got two black dots, so that’s a closed interval,
第一个例子中 有两个黑色点 所以是一个闭区间
and clearly you have a continuous function. There are no breaks in the graph.
显然 这是一个连续函数 图中没有间断点
You have an absolute minimum over here and an absolute maximum over there.
因此 这里是绝对最小值 那里是绝对最大值
That’s the first example. It attains an absolute maximum and minimum on the interval.
这是第一个例子 其在区间上存在一个绝对最大值和最小值点
On the other hand, the second example is not in the scope of the discussion today
另一方面 第二个例子不在今天的讨论范围内
because you have over here a function which is not continuous. You can see over here that
因为这是一个不连续的函数 在图中的这个位置
there’s a sort of break in the graph. The theorem does not apply and you do not need to worry about
存在间断 该定理不适用 你无需担心
whether there are absolute maxima or minima, but of course in this case,
该函数是否存在绝对最大值或最小值 当然在这种情况下
you actually do not have them because the function seems to go off to minus infinity over here
实际并不存在绝对最大值或最小值 因为函数在这边趋向负无穷
and plus infinity over there. The last example is again not quite relevant
而在那边趋向正无穷 最后一个例子也不太相关
because here you have an open interval. Because the interval is not closed, or is open,
因为函数定义在开区间上 即区间不是封闭的 而是开放的
therefore you cannot guarantee anything from the extreme value theorem. But in fact in this case,
因此你不能由极值定理上得到什么结论 事实上在这个例子中
there is neither an absolute maximum or minimum precisely because of the issue of missing endpoints.
正因为区间缺少端点 所以函数既没有绝对最大值 也没有最小值
Okay. The question now is how do we actually find these extreme values.
接下来的问题是如何求出极值
The best tool we have for this is Fermat’s theorem given by Pierre de Fermat a long time ago.
解决这个问题的最好工具是皮埃尔·德·费马多年前给出的费马定理
What that does is it lets us find local maxima and minima. What it says is if f has
费马定理能让我们求得局部最大值和最小值 其内容是如果f存在
a local maximum or minimum, then its derivative at that point must be 0. For example,
局部最大值或最小值 那么函数在该点的导数必为0 例如
if you look at the earlier function, then the claim is that it’s got local maxima and minima over here and there,
回顾前面的这个函数 它在该点和那点存在局部最大值和最小值
and you can check that with the derivatives at those points. They are both 0,
你可以检查这些点的导数 都是0
so Fermat’s theorem will say that that’s the condition to be satisfied for local maxima and minima.
根据费马定理 这就是局部最大值和最小值需要满足的条件
Okay. There are a few things to remember about Fermat’s theorem. The converse is not true,
关于费马定理有几个需要注意的点 费马定理的逆命题并不成立
and it’s not true in a few ways. For example, we have a function over here, a cubed function,
不成立的原因有几方面 例如 这是一个三次函数
and clearly you have a horizontal tangent over here. The derivative is 0,
显然 函数具有在该点处具有水平切线 导数是0
and yet there are no maxima or minima. The theorem mainly says that if you have
却没有最大值和最小值 费马定理说的是如果存在
a maximum or minimum, then the derivative must be 0. The other example is
最大值或最小值 那么导数一定是0 另一个例子是
the absolute value function where you do have a minimum, but then the derivative does not exist at that point.
绝对值函数 函数的确存在一个最小值 但是该点导数不存在。
Fermat’s theorem must be used with caution, but it is in fact a very powerful theorem.
费马定理一定要谨慎使用 不过它也确实是一个非常强大的定理
Fermat’s theorem is really talking about what are called critical numbers.
费马定理其实讨论的是驻点
When you want to look for maxima and minima, you need to look for what are called critical numbers.
当你要求最大值和最小值时 你需要求出驻点
What’s a critical number? Well, a critical number is a number where either you have a 0 derivative
什么是驻点？驻点是令导数为0
or the derivative does not exist. For example, the cube root function has a critical point
或导数不存在的数 例如 立方根函数的驻点
over here because the derivative is not defined there.
在这里 因为该点导数无定义
Of course, the local maxima and minima are good places to look for critical points.
局部最大值和最小值点也是寻找驻点的位置
With all that information, we are now ready to put together a method for finding absolute maxima and minima.
综上所述 将求绝对最大值和最小值的方法总结归纳
That’s what is called the closed interval method. What it says is to find the absolute maximum
方法是所谓的闭区间法 为找到闭区间上连续函数的绝对最大值
and minimum of a continuous function on a closed interval, you first of all find out
和最小值 你首先要求出所有
the critical numbers, find out the values of the function at those critical numbers,
驻点 并求出驻点处的函数值
then you work out the value at the endpoints and then the largest of all those values
再计算出区间端点的函数值 取以上这些值中最大的一个
is the absolute maximum and the smallest value will be the absolute minimum.
作为绝对最大值 最小值则为绝对最小值
As an example, here’s a cubic function. We find the derivative, set it equal to 0 and figure out
举例说明 这是一个三次函数 先求导数 令其为0 然后计算出
that 1 is a critical point. Add that 1 to the list 0 and 2. You’ve got to look at 0, 1 and 2.
那1是一个驻点 将1添加到0和2的求解列表中 需要关注的是0 1和2
0 and 2 are the endpoints of the interval, 1 is a critical point, and you find that
因为0和2是区间端点 1是临界点 可以求得
the minimum value occurs at −1 and the maximum value occurs at 2.
最小值为-1 最大值为2
You have an absolute maximum at (2, 2) and you have an absolute minimum at (−1, 1).
则绝对最大值在（2，2）取得 绝对最小值在（-1，1）取得
We have two very nice functions called Maximize and Minimize which will do that automatically for you, and there you are.
Wolfram语言包含有两个很有用的函数 Maximize和Minimize 可以自动求得最大最小值 如下所示
It says that the maximum is at (2, 2)
结果显示 最大值点为（2，2）
and the minimum is at (−1, 1), just as we learned earlier on. But the closed interval method
而最小值点在（-1，1） 与前面求得的结果一致 闭区间法
is the basic tool for finding maxima and minima on a closed interval.
是在闭区间上寻找最大值和最小值的基本工具
As an application, let’s take this example. We have the cost function for a business,
作为应用 这个例子包含一个企业的成本函数
and the question is to find the number of units x that minimize the cost. What you do is
需要求得使成本最小的商品数量x 你需要做的是
you find the critical points. There’s just one over here. It’s about 6,790.
求出驻点 驻点只有一个大约为6790
You plug in the critical point and the endpoints over here. Then what you do is you work out
再将驻点和端点代入 计算出
the values at those points, and you find out that you need to produce around 6,790 units
在这些点处的成本 可以得出 需要生产大约6790件商品
to minimize the cost. Here’s a plot for the problem, and you can see quite clearly that
使成本最小化 以下成本函数的图像 可以清晰地看到
you actually do have a minimum somewhere around 7,000. That’s the end of this lesson.
函数存在一个最小值点在7000附近 至此 本次课接近尾声了
Let’s summarize. We certainly realize that optimization is a crucial component of our lives from day to day.
我们来总结一下 我们意识到 优化是我们日常生活中至关重要的组成部分
Different people will use it in different ways. For example, businesses will want
不同的人会在不同场合使用优化 例如 企业希望
to make the most money with the least amount of cost, while drivers might want to reduce
以最小的成本赚取最大的利润 而司机们想节省
the time that they take to go from one place to another. The basic tool in this area is Fermat’s theorem,
从一个地方到另一个地方所花费的时间 优化问题的基本工具是费马定理
which lets us find the critical numbers for a function. The closed interval method is
费马定理让我们求得函数的驻点 而闭区间法是
a complete method for finding the absolute maxima and minima. That’s the end of this lesson.
求绝对最大值和最小值的完整方法 本次课到此结束了
The next lesson will talk about the mean value theorem, a very important theorem in calculus.
下节课将要讲均值定理 这是微积分中非常重要的定理
But before we do that, please do review today’s lesson, look at the exercises and make sure that
在这之前 请大家先务必复习一下今天的课程 看看习题 确定
you’re ready for the next lesson on the mean value theorem. Thank you very much. I’ll stop over here.
准备好上下一节关于均值定理的课 非常感谢！本次课就到这里